Winona Fletcher Collection, 1939-1987, bulk 1982-1987 SC 2
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Winona Fletcher Collection
1939-1987
1982-1987
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Fletcher, Winona L.
SC 2
3 document cases 1.05 linear feet
519 Slides
9 Audiocassettes
9 Videocassettes VHS
1 video disc DVD
1 Videotape Reel
1 Audiotape Reel
This collection documents the activities of Dr. Winona Fletcher as Producing Director of the Indiana University Afro-American Arts Institute's 1986 revival of the Federal Theatre Project's 1939 production Prelude to Swing, entitled Prelude to Swing +50.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series:
Series 1: Personal Papers
Series 2: Audiovisual Materials
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Winona Fletcher taught theatre and drama at Kentucky State College (later University) from 1951 to 1978 and at Indiana University from 1978 to 1994. From 1971-73, while on leave from Kentucky State, she came to IU to assist in the development of the Afro-American Studies Department. Dr. Fletcher has been very involved with a number of theatre organizations, most notably through her work with the Kennedy Center, her research and work with the American College Theatre Festival Lorraine Hansberry contest for new playwrights, and her research into the Negro units of the Federal Theatre Project of the 1930s. Some of the other theatre organizations with which she has been prominently associated include the American Theatre Association, the University & College Theatre Association, the National Association of Dramatic and Speech Arts, the Association for Theatre in Higher Education, the Black Theatre Network, and the National Conference of African American Theatre.
Dr. Fletcher also served as a theater educator, historian, and author as well as a civic and social leader in her community, sorority, and church. During her tenure at at Indiana University, Fletcher served as Producing Director for the Afro-American Arts Institute's 1986 revival of Prelude to Swing entitled Prelude to Swing +50.
Access Restrictions
Use of time-based media materials (audio and video) may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Access to streaming audio, moving image, and full resolution digital image materials may currently be restricted to researchers who can authenticate with an IU account or who are physically present on campus. Remote streaming to individual researchers may be allowed with the completion of applicable forms.
For further information about access to online audiovisual materials, contact AAAMC staff at aaamc@indiana.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Winona Fletcher to the AAAMC on 1993 June 25.
Related Materials
Winona Lee Fletcher Papers (Accession no.: 1997MS02). CESKAA, Kentucky State University.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 3 boxes of documents pertaining to Indiana University's Afro-American Arts Institute's Prelude to Swing +50, a revival of the Federal Theatre Project's 1939 production of Prelude to Swing. The collection includes materials related to Fletcher's research of the Federal Theatre Project, personal correspondence and notes related to the Afro-American Arts Institute, production notes related to the 1986 theatrical production of Prelude to Swing +50, and the 1987 television documentary aired by WTIU under the same name. Also included are two 3-ring binders of slides intended for use in Prelude to Swing +50; 9 audiocassettes of rehearsals, show cues, and a 1986 performance of Prelude to Swing +50 produced in Fort Wayne, IN; 9 videocassettes containing excerpts from the 1986 performance; and 1 DVD of the 1987 documentary.
The 1939 production of Prelude to Swing was directed by Malvina Fried with Carlton Moss and was first performed in Philadelphia. The musical revue featured dancers, a black chorus, and a swing orchestra.
Musicals--Production and direction; Documentary television programs; African American theatre; African Americans--Social life and customs; United States--Social life and customs--19th century; United States--Social life and customs--20th century; Theater--United States--History--19th century; Theater--United States--History--20th century; African Americans--Music; African Americans--Civil rights; Civil rights movements--United States--History--20th century; Slavery--Drama; Slaves--United States--Social conditions; Fletcher, Winona L.; Afro-American Arts Institute, Indiana University; Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
- 1. Print and Photographic Materials, circa 1939-1987; 3 Boxes + 519 slides
  - 1.1. Personal Papers, 1983-1987
    - Afro-American Arts Institute Miscellaneous, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Studies, Blacks in Higher Education, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Studies, Blacks in Higher Education II, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Afro-American Studies, Blacks in Higher Education Newsletters, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Biography (Indiana University Department of Afro-American Studies Newsletter), 1984 (Box 1)
    - Black Theatre (NADSA Newsletter), 1984 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985 (Box 1)
  - 1.2. Prelude to Swing Research, 1939-1987
    - Correspondence with Library of Congress, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Federal Theatre Project, undated (Box 1)
    - Federal Theatre Project - Browne, Theodore, undated (Box 1)
    - Federal Theatre Project - Natural Man, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Federal Theatre Project (Newsletters), 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Federal Theatre Project - Run Little Chillin Miscellaneous (Original Script?), undated (Box 1)
    - Federal Theatre Project - Run Little Chillin (Reprinted Script), undated (Box 1)
    - Material for Prelude to Swing +50, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Articles, Bibliographies, Newsletters, Etc.), undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Notes (Manuscript Spiral Bound Notebook), undated (Box 1)
    - Prelude to Swing Production Material, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Prelude to Swing - Scripts, 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1.3. Prelude to Swing +50 Theatrical Production, 1985-1986
    - Captions for Slides (Computer Printout), 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Crew Notes, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Costumes (Sketches), 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Costumes - Notes (Plots, Inventories), 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Costumes - Measurement Charts, undated (Box 2)
    - Fletcher's Miscellaneous Manuscript Notes, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Notes for Slides, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Programs, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Program - Performance at Scottish Rite Auditorium, Fort Wayne, Indiana, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Promotional Materials - Mailers, Paper Flyers, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Publicity (Reviews), 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Scripts - Drafts and Notes, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Scripts - Final Script, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Set Design, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Set Design, Costume Charts (Oversized), 1986 (Box 2)
    - Sheet Music: Ranwalowo, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - 1.4. Prelude to Swing +50 Documentary Production, 1986-1987
    - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Fletcher Production Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Legal Documents, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Manuscript Documentary Production Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Manuscript Notes, Drafts, Articles, Programs, Etc.), 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscript Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Narration Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Promotional Materials - Invitations, Paper Flyers, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Publicity (Press Clippings, Reviews), 1987 (Box 3)
    - Video Technology Production Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - 1.5. Photographs: Production Staff Portraits, circa 1939-1987
    - Photocopied Portraits with Notes, circa 1986-1987; 16 Pages (Box 3)
    - Portraits of Prelude to Swing +50 Cast and Crew, circa 1986-1987; 10 photographs: black & white; 8 x 10 in. (Box 3)
    - Prelude to Swing (1939), circa 1986-1987; 7 photographs: black & white; 8 x 10 in. (Box 3)
    - Prelude to Swing +50 Production Photos, circa 1986-1987; 72 photographs: color + 12 photographs (black & white) (Box 3)
    - Prelude to Swing +50 Production Photo Negatives and Contact Sheets, circa 1986-1987; 53 negatives + 7 contact sheets (black & white) (Box 3)
    - Prelude to Swing +50 Production Portrait Negatives and Contact Sheets, circa 1986-1987; 32 negatives: black & white (Box 3)
    - Shaw University, 1986; 6 photographs: color (Box 3)
  - 1.6. Slides, circa 1939-1987; SL82--SL601; 401 Slides: black & white; + 119 slides (color; 2 x 2 in.); 2 x 2 in. (Box 4-5)
    Description
    Slides intended for use in 1986 production of Prelude to Swing +50
    Subjects:
    African American art
    African Americans--Civil rights
    African Americans--Music
    African Americans--Social life and customs
    Civil rights movements--United States--History--20th century
    Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
    Johns Island (S.C.: Island)
    Prelude to swing
    Prelude to swing +50
    Slavery--Drama
    Slaves--United States--Social conditions
    Theater--United States--History--20th century
    United States--Social life and customs--19th century
    United States--Social life and customs--20th century
- 2. Audiovisual Materials, 1980-1987; 9 Audiocassettes + 9 videocassettes (VHS), 1 videodisc (DVD), 1 audiotape reel, 1 videotape reel
  - 2.1. Performances, 1986-1977
    - Prelude to Swing +50 - Hours I and II, 1986 April 6; VC 476--VC 477; 2 Videocassettes: sound, color; (VHS) (Box 4-5)
    - Prelude to Swing +50 (Selected Excerpts) - Indiana University, 1986 April 5; VC 472; 1 Videocassette: sound, color; (VHS) (Box 4-5)
    - Prelude to Swing +50 (Documentary), Copy from Indiana University, Radio/TV, 1987 June 16; DVDR 33; Winniger, John; 1 video disc: digital, sound, color; (DVD) (Box 4-5)
      Location of Original(s)
      Copy of 1" master tape created by IU RadioTV.
    - Rehearsal Tape, 1986; cass 2348; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Prelude to Swing +50s Show Tape for Cues + Rehearsal, 1986; cass 2345; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Prelude to Swing +50 / Arranged & Composed by K.L. Ware, 1986; cass 2347; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Prelude to Swing +50 - Performance at Afro-American Arts Institute, Indiana University, Fort Wayne, 1986 March 1; cass 2346; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Studio Work Tape, 1987 April 30; VC 479; 1 Videocassette: sound, color; (VHS) (Box 4-5)
    - Dance Co. "Prelude +"; Intro. by Dr. Fletcher; Rehearsal at IU Auditorium, 1985 November 5 and; 1985 November 19; VC 471; 1 Videocassette: sound, color; (VHS) (Box 4-5)
    - Prelude to Swing +50, Performance Tapes, undated; VC 473--VC 475; 3 Videocassettes: sound, color; (VHS) (Box 4-5)
    - Prelude "B-Roll" with Timecode Burned in, undated; VC 478; 1 Videocassette: sound, color; (VHS) (Box 4-5)
  - 2.2. Research, undated
    - Gershwin Selections / André Previn, London Symphony Orchestra (Angel C140283), undated; cass 2349; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Big White Fog; Run Little Chillin (Unidentified Performers), undated; cass 2350; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Freydberg (Unidentified Selections), undated; cass 2351; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Musical Selections / Various Artists (Compilation from Commercial Recordings?), undated; cass 2352; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Musical Selections by Charlie Parker, Cole Porter (Compilation from Commercial Recordings?), undated; cass 2353; 1 Audiocassette: analog (Box 4-5)
    - Carlton Moss Recording for Prelude to Swing, 1985 December 15; OR 110; 1 Audiotape Reel (Box 4-5)
    - Ida Bell's Fortune, 1972 Summer; RV 7; 1 Videotape Reel (Box 4-5)